<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="https://cwrc.ca/templates/css/tei.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Linking Ontologies and Vocabularies for Medieval Studies</title>
				<author><persName> Toby Burrows</persName></author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<distributor>Canadian Writing Research Collaboratory</distributor>
				<address>
					<addrLine>University of Guelph</addrLine>
				</address>
				<availability>
					<p>Available under a CC-BY-NC license</p>
				</availability>
				<date>when="2019"&gt;2019</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl> Title of work, Ontologies for Linked Data in the Humanities, 2019) prepared
					for the Ontologies for Linked Dara in the Humanities Workshop at the DH2019
					conference in Utrecht, sponsored by the <orgName>Alliance for the Digital
						Humanities Linked Open Data Special Interest Group</orgName>, and organized
					by <persName>Kim Martin</persName> and <persName>Susan Brown</persName> with
					committee members <persName>Johanna Drucker</persName>, <persName>Ryan
						Shaw</persName>, <persName>Joseph T. Tennis</persName>, and
						<persName>Jasmine Drudge-Willson</persName>….</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<xenoData><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:as="http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#" xmlns:cwrc="http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.geonames.org/ontology#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">

<rdf:Description rdf:datatype="http://www.w3.org/TR/json-ld/"><![CDATA[
{
	"@context": {
		"dcterms:created": {
			"@type": "xsd:dateTime",
			"@id": "dcterms:created"
		},
		"dcterms:issued": {
			"@type": "xsd:dateTime",
			"@id": "dcterms:issued"
		},
		"oa:motivatedBy": {
			"@type": "oa:Motivation"
		},
		"@language": "en",
		"rdf": "http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#",
		"rdfs": "http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#",
		"as": "http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#",
		"cwrc": "http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#",
		"dc": "http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/",
		"dcterms": "http://purl.org/dc/terms/",
		"foaf": "http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/",
		"geo": "http://www.geonames.org/ontology#",
		"oa": "http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#",
		"schema": "http://schema.org/",
		"xsd": "http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#"
	},
	"@id": "https://github.com/placeholder/blob/master/placeholder.xml?title_annotation_20200805110340914",
	"@type": "oa:Annotation",
	"dcterms:created": "2020-08-05T15:03:40.914Z",
	"dcterms:issued": "2020-08-05T15:03:54.652Z",
	"dcterms:creator": {
		"@id": "http://id.cwrc.ca/user/placeholder",
		"@type": [
			"cwrc:NaturalPerson",
			"schema:Person"
		],
		"cwrc:hasName": "Placeholder",
		"foaf:nick": "plchldr"
	},
	"oa:motivatedBy": "oa:identifying",
	"oa:hasTarget": {
		"@id": "https://github.com/placeholder/blob/master/placeholder.xml?title_annotation_20200805110340914#Target",
		"@type": "oa:SpecificResource",
		"oa:hasSource": {
			"@id": "https://github.com/placeholder/blob/master/placeholder.xml",
			"@type": "dctypes:Text",
			"dc:format": "text/xml"
		},
		"oa:renderedVia": {
			"@id": "https://cwrc-writer.cwrc.ca/",
			"@type": "as:Application",
			"rdfs:label": "CWRC Writer",
			"schema:softwareVersion": "1.0"
		},
		"oa:hasSelector": {
			"@id": "https://github.com/placeholder/blob/master/placeholder.xml?title_annotation_20200805110340914#Selector",
			"@type": "oa:XPathSelector",
			"rdf:value": "TEI/text/body/div/div[4]/p[2]/title"
		}
	},
	"oa:hasBody": {
		"@type": "bf:Title",
		"@id": "https://commons.cwrc.ca//islandora:3b729647-5e55-4e8e-96c6-1c98dbe1986d",
		"dc:format": "text/plain"
	},
	"as:generator": {
		"@id": "https://cwrc-writer.cwrc.ca/",
		"@type": "as:Application",
		"rdfs:label": "CWRC Writer",
		"schema:url": "https://cwrc-writer.cwrc.ca",
		"schema:softwareVersion": "1.0"
	},
	"oa:hasCertainty": "cwrc:high"
}
]]></rdf:Description></rdf:RDF></xenoData><xenoData/>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p> This paper examines the use of Linked Data ontologies and vocabularies in the
					research field of medieval studies, based on work done by the “Mapping
					Manuscript Migrations” (MMM) project since 2017. This has included applying a
					unified data model and reconciling data for five main classes of entities:
					Persons, Places, Organizations, Works, and Manuscripts. For each of these
					classes, we review the identifiers used in MMM’s source datasets, and note the
					way in which these tend to rely on generic vocabularies rather than specialist
					medieval ones. We also suggest some directions for building a more specialized
					Linked Data environment for medieval studies in the future. </p>
			</abstract>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>TEI</term>
					<term>text encoding</term>
					<term>conversison</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>

			<div type="chapter">
				<head><bibl><title type="a">Linking Ontologies and Vocabularies for Medieval
							Studies<lb/></title><author><persName key="Burrows, Toby." ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/93723421/">Toby
								Burrows</persName><note>University of Oxford</note></author>
					</bibl>
				</head> <p>This paper examines the use of Linked Data ontologies and vocabularies in
				the research field of medieval studies, based on work done by the “<orgName ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca//cwrc:9b7e8291-1609-490b-b98a-cd1d5020e50c" key="Mapping Manuscript Migrations" cert="high">Mapping Manuscript
					Migrations</orgName>” (MMM) project since <date when="2017" cert="high">2017</date>. This has included applying a unified data model and reconciling
				data for five main classes of entities: Persons, Places, Organizations, Works, and
				Manuscripts. For each of these classes, we review the identifiers used in <orgName key="Mapping Manuscript Migrations" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca//cwrc:9b7e8291-1609-490b-b98a-cd1d5020e50c">MMM</orgName>’s source datasets, and note the way in which these tend to rely
				on generic vocabularies rather than specialist medieval ones. We also suggest some
				directions for building a more specialized Linked Data environment for medieval
				studies in the future.</p><div type="sub-section">
					<head>Context</head>
					<p>Medieval studies is a large field of research, covering the entire history
						and culture of <placeName key="Western Europe">Western Europe</placeName>
						for more than a thousand years, from the fifth to the fifteenth centuries.
						The major conferences, like the annual <orgName ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q17081602" key="International Medieval Congress" cert="high">International Medieval
							Congress</orgName> in <placeName key="Leeds England United Kingdom" ref="http://geonames.org/2644688">Leeds</placeName>, contain more than
						750 sessions with over 2,500 participants. There is a vast literature of
						printed and electronic publications, and an increasingly complex environment
						of digital resources of many different kinds. In this digital environment,
						however, there is nothing resembling the recent initiatives in closely
						related research fields (especially classics and ancient history, and early
						modern studies) to develop tools and resources for data linkage. At the
						heart of these initiatives is Linked Open Data – both as a paradigm and as a
						set of specifications, tools, and methodologies, loosely coordinated by the
							<orgName key="Linked Pasts Network" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q73896570">Linked Pasts
							Network</orgName>. [1]</p>
					<p>In this paper, we examine the current situation in medieval studies and
						present proposals for future directions in the application of Linked Open
						Data to this research field. Our proposals build on work already being
						carried out as part of the “Mapping Manuscript Migrations” (MMM) project, an
						international collaboration between the <orgName ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca//cwrc:aeff80c3-fe57-4c0c-ba7c-4c39d79836bf" key="Oxford University" cert="high">University of Oxford</orgName>, the
							<orgName key="University of Pennsylvania" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca//cwrc:4b300b27-92f1-4577-bb0e-6553e8704ef5">University of Pennsylvania</orgName>, <orgName key="Aalto University" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q300980">Aalto University</orgName>,
						and the <orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/136837194/" key="Institut de recherche et d'histoire des textes France" cert="high">Institut de recherche et d’histoire des textes</orgName>. [2] Funded by
						the Trans-Atlantic Platform under its Digging into Data Challenge for <date from="2017" to="2020" cert="high">2017-2020</date>, Mapping Manuscript
						Migrations focuses on aggregating data from four major data sources relating
						to medieval manuscripts: the <orgName key="Schoenberg Database of Manuscripts (SDBM)" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q94994669">Schoenberg Database of
							Manuscripts</orgName>, <orgName key="Medieval Manuscripts in Oxford Libraries" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q84825958">Medieval Manuscripts in
							Oxford Libraries</orgName>, <orgName ref="http://bibale.irht.cnrs.fr/" key="Bibale" cert="high">Bibale</orgName>, and Medium. The methodologies
						being deployed include a unified data model derived from the <orgName ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q624005" key="CIDOC Conceptual Reference Model" cert="high">CIDOC-CRM</orgName>
						and <orgName ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q5427036" key="FRBRoo" cert="high">FRBROO</orgName> ontologies, and a matching and
						reconciliation process based on Linked Data identifiers and
						vocabularies.</p>
					<p>For the MMM project, the main ontological classes are Manuscripts, Persons,
						Organizations, Places, and Works. While the Manuscripts class could be
						expanded to cover Objects more broadly, manuscripts are the most common
						surviving type of object from the medieval period and the most valuable
						evidence from a range of interdisciplinary research perspectives. As well as
						being the main focus of medieval research, they exemplify most of the issues
						connected with the deployment of Linked Data ontologies and
						vocabularies.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="sub-section">
					<head>Data model</head>
					<p>Each of the source datasets involved in the <orgName ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca//cwrc:9b7e8291-1609-490b-b98a-cd1d5020e50c" key="Mapping Manuscript Migrations" cert="high">MMM</orgName> project
						have their own preconditions and goals, and thus follow their own data
						modeling conventions. The Schoenberg Database records primarily provenance
						events and observations of manuscripts at specific points in time, based on,
						e.g., auction catalogs, while in Bibale and the Bodleian catalogue the main
						focus is on describing manuscripts as objects. In order to aggregate the
						datasets and use them with shared user interfaces and tools for answering a
						wide range of research questions, a unified data model for harmonizing them
						is needed.</p>
					<p>The model applied in the project is based on the <orgName ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q624005" key="CIDOC Conceptual Reference Model" cert="high">CIDOC-CRM</orgName>
						and <orgName ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q5427036" key="FRBRoo" cert="high">FRBROO</orgName> ontologies, where the essential distinction
						between works, expressions, manifestations, and items are considered [3].
						The most essential core classes in the model are (1) physical manuscript
						objects with properties such as shelf-mark, owner and title, and (2)
						provenance events that describe events related to the manuscripts, such as
						production, appearance in an auction, acquisition, etc. These ontologies
						were chosen as the basis because they are modern standards for data
						harmonization in museums and libraries, respectively, and they support
						event-based modeling needed in modeling provenance data that are essentially
						chains of events concerning the manuscript objects.</p>
					<p>The <orgName ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q624005" key="CIDOC Conceptual Reference Model" cert="high">CIDOC-CRM</orgName>
						and FRBROO ontologies have been extended in the MMM project to suit the
						modeling needs of the source databases. Extensions include 1) subclasses of
						crm:E54_Dimension for representing the height, width, and folio, column, and
						line count of the manuscript; 2) specific properties for linking the
						entities to source databases, such as to manuscript records, observation
						entries, and data providers; 3) subproperties of crm:P1_is_identified_by to
						express different shelfmark conventions; and 4) representation of the roles
						of participants in events, such as author, scribe, artist, binder, patron or
						selling agent.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="sub-section">
					<head>Places</head>
					<p>The majority of places in the source datasets for the <orgName ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/cwrc:9b7e8291-1609-490b-b98a-cd1d5020e50c" key="MMM" cert="high">MMM</orgName> project can be matched to
						identifiers from one or more of the most widely used generic Linked Open
						Data vocabularies: the <orgName ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1520117" key="Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names" cert="high">Getty Thesaurus of
							Geographical Names</orgName> (TGN) and GeoNames. TGN is much smaller
						than <orgName ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q830106" key="GeoNames" cert="high">GeoNames</orgName> but more historically oriented and
						actively curated. Neither has anything like the coverage of the gazetteers
						produced by mapping agencies. For <placeName key="United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland  United Kingdom" ref="http://geonames.org/2635167">Great Britain</placeName>, for
						example, TGN has only half as many places names as GeoNames, but this in its
						turn has only a fraction of the names provided by the Ordnance Survey.
						[4]</p>
					<p>The MMM datasets, in which medieval, early modern, and modern place names are
						all present, have their preferred default vocabulary: <persName key="GeoNames" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q830106">GeoNames</persName> for Bibale, and TGN for Schoenberg and Oxford. None
						of these datasets makes use of a gazetteer specifically designed to cover
						medieval places and their medieval names. This is partly, at least, because
						the evidence in the MMM source datasets focuses on the history of
						manuscripts in the post-medieval world. The places referred to are usually
						(though not always) the same as places which exist today, and they are
						usually presented in modern languages, not in Latin. For medieval places in
							<placeName key="England England United Kingdom" ref="http://geonames.org/6269131">England</placeName>, the best source
						of data is the <orgName ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca//cwrc:e10afbc6-fa1f-48da-81a4-9610726daf48" key="Survey of English Place Names" cert="high">Survey of English Place
							Names</orgName>, published by the English Place Name Society and
						digitized as part of the Historical Gazetteer of England’s Place-Names. This
						is not yet available as Linked Data, though its creators claimed that it
						would be “relatively easy to convert it to RDF”. [5]</p>
				</div>
				<div type="sub-section">
					<head>Persons</head>
					<p>In the source datasets for the <orgName ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/cwrc:9b7e8291-1609-490b-b98a-cd1d5020e50c" key="MMM" cert="high">MMM</orgName> project, “person” entities can cover
						everything from medieval authors to early modern owners to modern buyers and
						sellers of manuscripts. The three datasets are consistent in using VIAF
						identifiers as their primary source for persons. In the Schoenberg Database
						of Manuscripts, VIAF is the preferred source. In the Bodleian catalogue,
						VIAF identifiers are supplemented by other sources, including the Library of
							<orgName key="Library of Congress" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q131454">Congress</orgName>,
							<orgName key="Wikidata"><orgName ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q2013" key="Wikidata" cert="high">Wikidata</orgName></orgName>, <orgName key="SUDOC" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q2597810">Sudoc</orgName>, <orgName key="Gemeinsame Normadatei" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q94994694">Gemeinsame
							Normadatei</orgName> (GND), and the Oxford Dictionary of National
						Biography. Bibale also prefers <orgName key="VIAF">VIAF</orgName>, but adds
						identifiers from Wikidata and the ARK identifiers from the Bibliothèque
						nationale de <placeName key="Republic of France  France" ref="http://geonames.org/3017382">France</placeName>; <orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/309866856/" key="Biblissima - Bibliotheca bibliothecarum novissima (projekt)" cert="high">Biblissima</orgName> identifiers are also referenced.</p>
					<p>None of the MMM datasets makes reference to any specifically medieval name
						authorities. There are many lists and catalogues of medieval persons and
						their names, and a significant number of these are available in digital
						form. [6] It is worth noting that several of the digital sources are
						commercial products, distributed by publishers like <orgName key="Brepols" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q981917">Brepols</orgName>. These
						include Europa Sacra (with data on 30,000 church prelates) and the author
						indexes to the Library of Latin Texts. Some specific initiatives are already
						under way, including the work by the “Medieval Publishing” project at the
							<orgName key="University of Helsinki" ref="http://dbpedia.org/resource/University_of_Helsinki">University of
							Helsinki</orgName> to transform <persName key="Richard Sharpe" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/40146825568807632710/">Richard
							Sharpe</persName>’s <title ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca//islandora:3b729647-5e55-4e8e-96c6-1c98dbe1986d" key="The Seed Savers" level="m" cert="high">Handlist of the Latin Writers of Great Britain and
							<placeName key="Ireland  Ireland" ref="http://geonames.org/2963597">Ireland</placeName> before 1540</title> into database form. [7] Publishing this
						dataset as Linked Data is envisaged as a second stage for this project.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="sub-section">
					<head>Organizations</head>
					<p>Organizations are not always distinguished from places in the source datasets
						for the <orgName ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/cwrc:9b7e8291-1609-490b-b98a-cd1d5020e50c" key="MMM" cert="high">MMM</orgName> project. The interface to the Oxford
						manuscripts catalogue simply includes organizations in its browsable list of
						“places”. This is because the majority of these organizations are medieval
						religious houses of various kinds, which are usually known by a place name,
						such as “<placeName key="Abingdon Abbey" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q2820496">Abingdon</placeName>,
						Benedictine abbey”. Behind the scenes, however, they are linked to the VIAF
						(Virtual International Authority File) vocabulary. Other identifiers are
						also given, including Wikidata, the Library of Congress, Sudoc, and ARK
						identifiers from the Bibliothèque nationale de France.</p>
					<p>In the Schoenberg Database of Manuscripts, on the other hand, organizations
						are combined with persons into a “Names” file. These are both medieval and
						modern, and include a significant number of religious houses. A large
						proportion of the organizational names have been matched to <orgName ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q54919" key="Virtual International Authority File" cert="high">VIAF</orgName>
						identifiers. Bibale’s organizations consist mostly of libraries and other
						institutional owners of manuscripts (especially medieval and early modern
						religious houses). VIAF is again consistently used, accompanied by
						identifiers from the <orgName ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q193563" key="Bibliothèque nationale de France" cert="high">Bibliothèque
							nationale de France</orgName>, <orgName key="Biblissima - Bibliotheca bibliothecarum novissima (projekt)" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/309866856/">Biblissima</orgName>, and
						Wikidata.</p>
					<p>Organizations as a class raise various questions of scope and definition in a
						medieval context. In medieval England, for instance, Anglo-Saxon
						administrative units like “hundreds” could be considered primarily as
						places, since they were defined as geographical areas within a county or
						shire. But the Norman system of government overlaid on top of this framework
						after 1066 was less conceptually clear; the “honours” and “baronies” of the
						great lords consisted of various estates scattered across the country, which
						were primarily organizational and administrative in nature. [8] A specialist
						Linked Open Data vocabulary for medieval organizations in England could be
						drawn from existing lists of baronies and religious houses, together with
						data relating to offices within the structure of royal government and to the
						administrative hierarchy of the <orgName ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca//cwrc:3bf4fbbc-144c-40da-86d2-07550471c7b0" key="Church of England" cert="high">Church</orgName>.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="sub-section">
					<head>Works</head>
					<p>The Works class is problematic in the source datasets for the <orgName ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/cwrc:9b7e8291-1609-490b-b98a-cd1d5020e50c" key="MMM" cert="high">MMM</orgName> project. They contain very little in
						the way of links to external Linked Open Data identifiers for works, and
						some do not even distinguish “works” – or even titles – as a separate
						element in their data. The Schoenberg Database, for example, does not
						contain separate records for works or titles; they are simply recorded as
						part of the observation record. In the Oxford manuscript catalogue, on the
						other hand, the a provides a unique ID number for more than 12,000 works. It
						records the “uniform title” (author + work), the “manuscript title”, and the
						“normalised manuscript title”. There are more than 360 links to external
						identifiers – primarily Pinakes for Greek works and Mirabile for Latin
						works. Bibale distinguishes between “Oeuvre” (i.e., work) and the
						“Text/Edition” (i.e., manifestation). There are unique identifiers for both
						of these, but no links to external identifiers.</p>
					<p>There are numerous lists and catalogues of medieval religious and literary
						writings, and many of these are available in some kind of digital form. [6]
						Among the issues to be tackled here are the <title ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1845" key="Bible" level="m" cert="high" rend="normal">Bible</title> and its derivatives (the focus
						of much medieval writing, especially in the earlier Middle Ages); the
						multiplicity of anonymous works – often without any kind of title and often
						identifiable only by their opening words (their “incipit”); and the way in
						which many medieval “works” actually consist of annotations, commentaries,
						and glosses on earlier works, as well as re-workings and abridgements of
						them. The work of the “Medieval Authorship” project is relevant here too,
						since Sharpe’s Handlist identifies and provides titles for the writings of
						medieval British and Irish authors.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="sub-section">
					<head>Manuscripts</head>
					<p>Each of the <orgName ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/cwrc:9b7e8291-1609-490b-b98a-cd1d5020e50c" key="MMM" cert="high">MMM</orgName> source datasets attempts to go
						beyond simply using the shelf-mark and repository for identifying individual
						manuscripts. The Bibale database contains links to another IRHT database,
						Medium, where 109,000 manuscripts have their own ARK identifiers. In the
							<orgName ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca//cwrc:51e93649-642b-47d3-9b8c-c08d167dfc42" key="bodleian library" cert="high">Bodleian</orgName> catalogue, each
						manuscript has a unique ID number, but there is no authority list for
						manuscripts (unlike persons, places, organizations, and works). The creation
						of ARK identifiers for Oxford manuscripts is currently being investigated by
						the MMM project and the Bodleian Library. In the Schoenberg Database, each
						of the nearly 25,000 manuscript records has a unique URL, but they are not
						accompanied by links to any external identifiers or to an authoritative
						shelf-mark or title.</p>
					<p>The need for a system of Linked Data identifiers for medieval manuscripts is
						now broadly accepted, and has been the subject of several meetings over the
						last two years. Under the auspices of the <orgName key="Institut de recherche et d'histoire des textes (France)" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/1145602310801361359/">IRHT</orgName>, a
						project has been established to develop and test a specification for an
						International Standard Manuscript Identifier or ISMI. [9] There is still
						considerable work to be done in defining the scope and purpose of ISMI, as
						well as in confirming and building the technical solution. Even when the
						ISMI registry is operational, it will still take a major effort to create
						and embed these identifiers in local databases for manuscripts with known
						and established current institutional locations and shelf-marks.
						Nevertheless, ISMI has the potential to revolutionize medieval manuscript
						studies by enabling large-scale inter-linking of heterogeneous manuscript
						data.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="sub-section">
					<head>Conclusion</head>
					<p>We believe that it is critical to develop, publish and re-use Linked Open
						Data ontologies and vocabularies in order to further the interoperability of
						digital resources for medieval studies. The combination of <orgName ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q624005" key="CIDOC Conceptual Reference Model" cert="high">CIDOC-CRM</orgName>
						and <orgName ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q5427036" key="FRBRoo" cert="high">FRBROO</orgName> ontologies, with some extensions, appears
						to function as a suitable data model for representing manuscripts. The more
						generalist vocabularies like <orgName ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q54919" key="Virtual International Authority File" cert="high">VIAF</orgName>
						and <orgName ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1520117" key="Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names" cert="high">TGN</orgName>
						already have a reasonably good coverage of medieval persons, places, and
						organizations, as the MMM project has been able to demonstrate. But the
						level of that coverage has been inflated to some extent by the scope of
						datasets relevant to manuscript research, since they include many early
						modern and modern names as well as medieval ones.</p>
					<p>The next priority for medieval studies should be the conversion of existing
						specialist vocabularies to Linked Data formats, accompanied by an
						investigation of ways in which they can be associated with the more general
						vocabularies. The work being done by the “Medieval Publishing” project
						provides a possible model here. While persons, places, and organizations
						might be considered the “low-hanging fruit” in this context, it will be more
						important and valuable for the longer term to tackle the more complex issues
						around works and manuscripts – the latter within the framework envisaged by
						the ISMI initiative.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="sub-section">
					<head>References</head>
					<listBibl>
						<anchor/>
						<bibl><title><orgName ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q73896570" key="Linked Pasts Network" cert="high">Linked
								Pasts</orgName></title>, <ref target="http://linkedpasts.org">http://linkedpasts.org</ref>, last accessed <date>4 May <date when="2019" cert="high">2019</date></date>.</bibl>
						<bibl><persName>
								<persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/169304061/" key="Hyvönen, Eero" cert="high" type="real">Hyvönen, E.</persName></persName>,
									<persName><persName ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca//cwrc:e72b34fc-cd6c-4493-96e1-83aff6cea96e" cert="high" type="real">Ikkala, E.</persName></persName>,
									<persName><persName ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca//cwrc:2888a86c-1116-453a-85f4-b60923c9ddcf" cert="high" type="real">Tuominen, J.</persName></persName> et
							al.: “<title>A Linked Open Data Service and Portal for Pre-Modern
								Manuscript Research</title>”, DHN 2019 Conference (<date when="2019" cert="high">2019</date>), <ref target="https://seco.cs.aalto.fi/publications/2019/hyvonen-et-al-dhn-mmm-2019.pdf">https://seco.cs.aalto.fi/publications/2019/hyvonen-et-al-dhn-mmm-2019.pdf</ref>,
							last accessed <date><date when="2019-05-04" cert="high">4 May
									2019</date></date>.</bibl>
						<bibl><persName><persName ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca//cwrc:b2b74e1b-9af1-4734-8f6a-cc2220e8a18d" cert="high" type="real">De Sabbata, S.</persName></persName>,
									<persName><persName ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca//cwrc:fddd41d9-a0df-4cf7-a5a5-723346154022" cert="high" type="real">Acheson, E.</persName></persName>:
								“<title>Geographies of gazetteers in Great Britain</title>”, 24th
							GIS Research UK (GISRUK 2016) Conference (<date when="2016" cert="high">2016</date>), <ref target="https://lre/le/ac/uk/handle/2381/38182">https://lre/le/ac/uk/handle/2381/38182</ref>, last accessed
									<date><date when="2019-05-04" cert="high">4 May
								2019</date></date>.</bibl>
						<bibl><persName><persName ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca//cwrc:0e06ee21-6eca-4edc-973e-cef3311eb776" cert="high" type="real">Le Bœuf, P.</persName></persName>:
								“<title>Modeling rare and unique documents: Using FRBROO/CIDOC
								CRM</title>”, <orgName ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q15763445" key="Journal of Archival Organization" cert="high">Journal of
								Archival Organization</orgName> 10(2), pp. 96–106 (<date when="2012" cert="high">2012</date>), <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/15332748.2012.709164">https://doi.org/10.1080/15332748.2012.709164</ref>, last accessed
								<date>9 May 2019</date>.</bibl>
						<bibl><persName><persName ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca//cwrc:909b6bc0-8f43-434b-978b-3497ec757f98" key="Claire Grover" cert="medium" type="real">Grover,
									C.</persName></persName>, <persName><persName ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca//cwrc:a536cf83-ad78-494e-81fa-962eee98a064" key="Tobin, Richard" cert="high" type="real">Tobin,
									R.</persName></persName>: “<title cert="high">A Gazetteer
								and Georeferencing for English Historical Documents</title>”,
							Proceedings of the 8th Workshop on Language Technology for Cultural
							Heritage, Social Sciences, and Humanities (LaTeCH) @ EACL 2014, pp.
							119-127 (<date when="2014" cert="high">2014</date>), <ref target="http://www.aclweb.org/anthology/W14-0617">http://www.aclweb.org/anthology/W14-0617</ref>, last accessed
								<date>4 May 2019</date>.</bibl>
						<bibl><persName>Wright, C.</persName>: <title>Manuscript Research:
								Identifying Texts and Locating Secondary Literature</title>, <ref target="https://bibliography.arc-humanities.org/manuscript-research-identifying-texts-and-locating-secondary-literature/">https://bibliography.arc-humanities.org/manuscript-research-identifying-texts-and-locating-secondary-literature/</ref>,
							last accessed <date>4 March 2019</date>.</bibl>
						<bibl><title>Medieval Publishing from c. 1000 to 1500</title>, <ref target="https://www.helsinki.fi/en/researchgroups/medieval-publishing">https://www.helsinki.fi/en/researchgroups/medieval-publishing</ref>,
							last accessed <date>4 March 2019</date>.</bibl>
						<bibl><persName><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/92521247/" key="Sanders, I. J." cert="high" type="real">Sanders,
									I.</persName></persName>: <title cert="high">English
								Baronies: a Study of their Origin and Descent , 1086-1327</title>.
									<publisher><orgName ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca//cwrc:c5d0d2f5-2978-4c22-bc10-22f5ca809e97" key="Oxford University Press" cert="high">Oxford University
									Press</orgName>, Oxford</publisher> (<date when="1960" cert="high">1960</date>).</bibl>
						<bibl><persName><persName ref="https://www.irht.cnrs.fr/?q=fr/annuaire/cassin-matthieu" key="Cassin, M." cert="high" type="real">Cassin,
								M.</persName></persName>: <title>ISMI: International Standard
								Manuscript Identifier: Project of Unique and Stable Identifiers for
								Manuscripts</title> (<date when="2018" cert="high">2018</date>),
								<ref target="https://www.manuscript-cultures.uni-hamburg.de/files/mss_cataloguing_2018/Cassin_pres.pdf">https://www.manuscript-cultures.uni-hamburg.de/files/mss_cataloguing_2018/Cassin_pres.pdf</ref>,
							last accessed <date>4 March 2019</date>.</bibl>
					</listBibl>
				</div>
			</div>

		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
